<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A seasonable memento both to King and people upon this critical juncture of affaires</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2232</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11907144</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11907144</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 511:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A seasonable memento both to King and people upon this critical juncture of affaires</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SEASONABLE MEMENTO Both to King and People Upon this CRITICAL JUNCTURE OF AFFAIRES.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Nullo modo eis Artibus placatur Divina Majeſtas, quibus Humana Dignitas inquinatur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civ. Dei.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50738:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50738:2"/>
            <head>A SEASONABLE Memento, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is grown into a Cuſtom (I know) to ſmooth the way for the <hi>Groſſe</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> in Agitation, by ſome preliminary Apology or Complement to the <hi>Courteous Reader;</hi> but yet, for reaſons beſt known to my ſelf, I ſhall at this time paſs over the Ceremonious Flouriſh of an <hi>Introduction,</hi> and <hi>without Welt or Guard</hi> (as they ſay) fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my <hi>Province,</hi> which is to make out, That neither upon pretext of Religion, Perſonal Vices, Exceſſes in Government, or any other Colour whatſoever, the Subjects of the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>England</hi> may withdraw their <hi>Obedience,</hi> or make <hi>Hoſtile Reſiſtance</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> our preſent Sovereign; being by right of <hi>Inheritance</hi> juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſs'd of the <hi>Crown;</hi> his <hi>Title</hi> no way depending either upon his <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Moral</hi> Virtues; and the ſaid <hi>Subjects</hi> having receiv'd him, and acknowledged him for their <hi>Only Supreme Governour,</hi> done him <hi>Homage,</hi> and ſworn to him <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Allegeance, Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely</hi> and without <hi>Condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS for other Princes and Potentates, whether <hi>Elective</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, or ſuch as (at the Erection of them) were received by the <hi>Firſt</hi> King upon Expreſs <hi>Covenant,</hi> and only with a <hi>Conditional</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; (as is pretended by thoſe of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and <hi>Others;</hi>) of <hi>Theſe</hi> I ſhall not here diſcourſe. Neither ſhall I ſpeak of thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50738:3"/>
               <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> who acknowledge (in <hi>Spiritual</hi> Matters) a <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Juriſdiction</hi> in the <hi>Pope</hi> over them; who further ſtickleth (by neceſſary Relation and Dependency of the <hi>Temporal</hi> upon the <hi>Spiritual</hi>) to have alſo a <hi>Temporal Power</hi> over them, <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia;</hi> And hath often put this his <hi>Claim</hi> in Practice, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying his <hi>Spiritual Cenſure</hi> of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> with the <hi>Sentence</hi> of diſcharging <hi>Subjects</hi> of their <hi>Obedience</hi> to their Princes, and ſo conſequently of <hi>Depoſing</hi> them. Herewith I ſhall not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; None of Theſe <hi>Caſes</hi> being applicable to <hi>This</hi> in queſtion of King <hi>Charles,</hi> who is no <hi>Elective</hi> King, but holdeth his <hi>Crown</hi> by an Unqueſtionable <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> deriv'd to him by <hi>Deſcent</hi> from his Anceſtours, for the ſpace of more than Six hundred years: Neither was there ever any <hi>Pact</hi> or <hi>Condition</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> or any of his <hi>Progenitours,</hi> of <hi>Forfeiture;</hi> (which in This <hi>Caſe</hi> neither <hi>was,</hi> nor ever <hi>can be</hi> juſtly pretended.) True it is, that his Anceſtours and Himſelf have been pleaſed to limit and reſtrain their <hi>Legal Right</hi> by many Conceſſions and Laws, in ſome Caſes; as the making of <hi>Laws</hi> without Conſent of <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Levying of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> &amp;c. which he cannot <hi>Violate</hi> without great Injuſtice, as ſhall be after ſhown: But no ſuch <hi>Pact</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> can be produced, whereby, upon <hi>Breach,</hi> he <hi>Forfeiteth</hi> his <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> or maketh it <hi>Juſtifiable</hi> for his <hi>Subjects</hi> to take up <hi>Arms</hi> againſt, or to inflict <hi>Puniſhments</hi> upon his <hi>Perſon,</hi> either by <hi>Dethroning, Death,</hi> or <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Caſe likewiſe of <hi>Roman Catholick Princes</hi> no way concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Him,</hi> who acknowledgeth not in a <hi>Pope</hi> any ſuch <hi>Superiour Authority:</hi> So that whatſoever <hi>Pretences</hi> may be in ſome Caſes, concerning ſuch Princes as I have above ſpecifyed; (wherein I ſhall not preſume to deliver my Opinion) yet in the <hi>Preſent</hi> Caſe of <hi>Our</hi> King, there can be no colourable Pretence of <hi>taking Arms</hi> againſt Him, or of <hi>Depoſing</hi> Him; which I underſtand to be (in effect) when he is diveſted of his Juſt Regal <hi>Power;</hi> Or of the <hi>Impriſoning</hi> of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> which I underſtand to be not only when he is actually in <hi>Bonds,</hi> or lockt up in a <hi>Room;</hi> but alſo when the Liberty of <hi>Going,</hi> and the Freedom of <hi>Speaking</hi> is reſtrained, to ſuch Places, or Perſons, as <hi>Others</hi> ſhall pleaſe; and he remain under a <hi>Guard,</hi> not of his <hi>Own</hi> chuſing, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon him by <hi>Others.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:50738:3"/>
            <p>IT muſt be acknowledged, that the Kings of <hi>England</hi> derive their <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> from <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Norman;</hi> who, although he came in by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> yet his <hi>Succeſſours</hi> (conſidering that a <hi>Right</hi> Acquir'd by <hi>Force,</hi> may likewiſe be Recover'd by <hi>Force,</hi> by thoſe upon whom the forcible Intruſion was made) were pleaſed, by way of <hi>Pact</hi> and <hi>Stipulation,</hi> to limit and qualify that <hi>(Imperium Abſolutum) Abſolute Dominion</hi> which is acquired by <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> And the People of <hi>England</hi> thereupon did ſubmit themſelves to his <hi>Government;</hi> and thereby was Conſtituted <hi>Imperium Legitimum,</hi> a <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Rightfull Sovereignty;</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> remaining with <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> with <hi>Common Right;</hi> whereby they were freed from the <hi>Servitude</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and remain'd under a <hi>Free Subjection;</hi> whereunto they had by their voluntary Conſent ſubmitted themſelves.</p>
            <p>THE Kings likewiſe did recede from <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and remain'd with <hi>Supreme,</hi> but not with <hi>Abſolute Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>Free Subjection,</hi> I underſtand when a People live under <hi>Laws</hi> to which they have given a <hi>Free Conſent,</hi> and not under the <hi>Meer will</hi> of the Prince; and that they retain ſuch a <hi>Propriety</hi> in that which is their <hi>Own,</hi> that without <hi>Their</hi> Aſſent, or Legal <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture,</hi> it cannot be taken from them: And this is a true diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt a <hi>Free Subject,</hi> and a <hi>Slave</hi> or <hi>Servant. Quicquid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirit</hi> Servus, <hi>acquirit</hi> Domino; Liber, <hi>quod acquirit, acquirit</hi> Sibi; Whatſoever a <hi>Slave</hi> gets, he gets for his <hi>Maſter;</hi> but what a <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> gets, is for <hi>Himſelf.</hi> And ſo although the <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>All</hi> belongs ſolely to the <hi>Prince,</hi> yet <hi>Propriety</hi> refers to <hi>Every man;</hi> Dominium <hi>Totius apud</hi> Caeſarem, Proprietas <hi>apud</hi> Singulos.</p>
            <p>THE Difference that I underſtand betwixt a <hi>Supreme,</hi> and an <hi>Abſolute Empire,</hi> is, That in <hi>Abſolute Empire</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Peoples <hi>Obedience</hi> is onely the Sovereigns <hi>Will.</hi> So it is in <hi>Turky, Muſcovy,</hi> and all ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> as retein <hi>Entire</hi> the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt;</hi> and was in ſome ſort under the <hi>Roman Emperours</hi> after the <hi>Lex Regia</hi> was eſtabliſh'd by the <hi>Peoples</hi> Conſent; whereby they transferr'd their <hi>Entire Right</hi> unto <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Supreme Empire</hi> I underſtand to be, when a King has a <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi> and <hi>Sovereignty</hi> over <hi>all,</hi> but his <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> is limited and reſtrein'd by reciprocal <hi>Pacts, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Stipulations</hi> betwixt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50738:4"/>
               <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> which is the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the Crown of <hi>England:</hi> and to theſe <hi>Pacts</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>People</hi> are equally bound before God and man; and the <hi>King</hi> is as much bound to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to the <hi>Protection</hi> of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> and to the <hi>Obſervance</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> (not onely out of <hi>Religion,</hi> but even of <hi>Morall Honeſty</hi> alſo) as the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> is to <hi>Obedience.</hi> And he is not onely accountable to <hi>God,</hi> but even his <hi>People</hi> have certain Juſt and Legal wayes to ſeek <hi>Redreſs,</hi> wherein he ſhall do <hi>Wrong;</hi> notwithſtanding that <hi>Axiome</hi> of our <hi>Common Law,</hi> That <hi>the King can do no Wrong;</hi> which is falſe in many ſenſes, and may very well be call'd <hi>Fictio Juris,</hi> a kind of <hi>Metaphyſicall Fiction: Le Roy ne fait Tort,</hi> being onely to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the ordinary Courſe of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> which the King admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring by his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and not in <hi>Perſon,</hi> it is <hi>They</hi> that are the <hi>Wrong-doers,</hi> and not the <hi>King;</hi> and the <hi>Subject,</hi> againſt <hi>Them,</hi> is to ſeek his Remedy. For <hi>Kings</hi> may do <hi>Wrong,</hi> and be as wicked as <hi>Other</hi> men, commit <hi>Murther,</hi> and wrongfully take away Other mens <hi>Eſtates;</hi> which no <hi>Fiction</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> can make not to be <hi>Wrong;</hi> although his <hi>Perſon</hi> be exempt from <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> And that <hi>Abſtract</hi> Conſideration of the <hi>King,</hi> for his juſt <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Office,</hi> as it hath often, <hi>Heretofore,</hi> been ill us'd in way of <hi>Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> ſo, in our <hi>Late Troubles,</hi> there was as ill uſe made of it, on the <hi>Other</hi> hand; when the <hi>taking up Arms</hi> and the <hi>Fighting</hi> againſt him, was pretended not to be againſt the <hi>KING,</hi> but onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>CHARLES ST<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ART.</hi> But (to ſpeak in plain In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible Terms) a <hi>King</hi> both may do <hi>Wrong,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> may ſeek their <hi>Redreſs,</hi> in ſuch ſort as the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> allowes. And the difference betwixt King and Peoples <hi>Failing</hi> in their Reciprocall <hi>Duties,</hi> is not but that they <hi>do wrong</hi> alike, <hi>offend</hi> God alike, and are both of them liable to be queſtion'd, according to the Extent of the <hi>Law,</hi> by <hi>both</hi> their Conſents eſtabliſh'd. The <hi>Subjects</hi> tranſgreſſing the <hi>Law,</hi> ſhall be puniſh'd according to the quality and meaſure of the Offence: <hi>Felony,</hi> by the Loſs of their Goods and Chattles, and by a <hi>Milder</hi> Death; <hi>Treaſon</hi> by a more <hi>Severe</hi> Death, and Confiſcation both of Goods and Inheritance. But hereof they muſt be Convict, <hi>per Pares,</hi> by People of their <hi>own</hi> Condition, and adjudg'd by a <hi>Superiour Juriſdiction;</hi> which can be deriv'd <hi>Onely</hi> and <hi>Singly</hi> from the <hi>King.</hi> So that the <hi>King,</hi> not having his <hi>Peer,</hi> nor any of his <hi>Own</hi> Condition, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a <hi>Legal Tryall;</hi> and having no <hi>Juriſdiction Superiour</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50738:4"/>Himſelf, cannot be <hi>Adjudg'd</hi> or <hi>Sentenc'd</hi> by any: for neither the Extent of the <hi>Law,</hi> nor any Condition of the <hi>Pacts,</hi> or <hi>Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> do reach to the <hi>Puniſhing</hi> of the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the King, or the <hi>Forfeiture</hi> of his <hi>Dominion</hi> over us. Certain it is that (in <hi>Civill</hi> things) <hi>Tryalls</hi> may be, (and often are) brought againſt the King; and Kings do give way that the <hi>Judges</hi> be ſworn to do <hi>Equall Juſtice</hi> betwixt <hi>Them</hi> and their <hi>Subjects:</hi> and in points of <hi>Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>wrong,</hi> we may <hi>Remonſtrate</hi> our Grievances, and challenge <hi>Redreſs</hi> by our <hi>Petitions;</hi> which, if they be not condeſcended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, we may inſiſt upon them as our <hi>Right,</hi> and claim them as a <hi>Due,</hi> and not as of <hi>Grace:</hi> But yet we muſt do it by way of <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as being a Dutifull <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> bringing their <hi>Plea</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>King;</hi> for in <hi>other</hi> ſort He ought not to be <hi>Impleaded.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe <hi>Petitions</hi> of <hi>Right,</hi> we may alſo <hi>Remonſtrate,</hi> enter our <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> and take all thoſe Courſes which the <hi>Laws</hi> allow. Neither ought the King to take <hi>Offence</hi> at theſe Legall <hi>Conteſtations</hi> with him; becauſe, by his Aſſent unto the <hi>Laws,</hi> he hath Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto <hi>Them:</hi> Nay he ought, in <hi>Them,</hi> to do us <hi>Right;</hi> being oblig'd thereunto by the <hi>Law</hi> of God, by his <hi>Oath,</hi> and by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Honeſty</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi> But yet if he fail in all theſe Duties, Our <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> reacheth not to his <hi>Perſonall</hi> Puniſhment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is <hi>Sub Nullo niſi ſub Deo,</hi> under none but God; and the <hi>Law</hi> ſtops <hi>There,</hi> and tells us, <hi>Satis ſufficit ei ad paenam, quod De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um habet <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltorem,</hi> that it will be a ſufficient puniſhment to him that he hath <hi>God</hi> for an <hi>Avenger.</hi> Yet are we not altogether left without Remedy; for <hi>Kings</hi> although they be God's <hi>Vice-gerents,</hi> yet they cannot work as God does, ſaying <hi>Fiat,</hi> and it was done; Kings muſt work by <hi>Mediate</hi> Inſtruments; and if they command <hi>Illegal</hi> Things, the <hi>Executioners</hi> of them are Reſponſible, and muſt make ſatisfaction to the <hi>Parties injur'd.</hi> And therefore the King ought not <hi>Immediately</hi> to <hi>Impriſon,</hi> nor in <hi>Perſon</hi> to <hi>Execute</hi> any thing; becauſe that in caſe of <hi>Wrong-doing,</hi> the Subject would then be deſtitute of all means of <hi>Redreſs,</hi> in regard the King's <hi>Perſon</hi> is not to be <hi>Impleaded</hi> by <hi>Law.</hi> I know the uſual Objections, <hi>In caſe Kings</hi> will <hi>do that which they ought</hi> not <hi>to do, and will, by their own</hi> immediate Warrants <hi>Commit, and be the Perſonall Actours of the Injuries, or not ſuffer the Executioners of their Illegal Commands to be Legally proceded againſt; ſhall the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject be left wholly without</hi> Remedy, <hi>and debarr'd the Benefit of that</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50738:5"/>Right <hi>of</hi> Nature, <hi>in-bred in all</hi> Creatures, <hi>of</hi> ſelf Preſervation? Yes; we muſt be contented with that <hi>Condition</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> hath placed us; and wherein, by our <hi>Own</hi> Conſents, and Stipulations of <hi>Subjection, We</hi> have placed our ſelves; and may onely right our ſelves by thoſe means which, by the <hi>Laws,</hi> (whereunto we have given our Conſent) are permitted unto us: Neither is our <hi>Native Liberty</hi> hereby raviſh'd from us; but as we have <hi>parted</hi> with it by our own <hi>Voluntary agreement,</hi> ſo neither can we <hi>reſume</hi> it, but by thoſe wayes which we have reſerv'd in the Stipulations of our <hi>Submiſſion.</hi> And beſide that herein there is no <hi>Injury,</hi> for that <hi>Volenti non fit Injuria;</hi> it would be more <hi>Hurtfull</hi> to Mankind, if it were <hi>Otherwiſe:</hi> for there is a neceſſity that in all ſorts of <hi>Governments,</hi> as well as in <hi>Monarchy,</hi> there ſhould be an <hi>Impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> ſomewhere, of not being <hi>queſtion'd;</hi> otherwiſe all would be hurl'd into <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion;</hi> Neither could there be any finall <hi>Determination</hi> of Controverſies, if there were not a <hi>Derniere Reſſort,</hi> and <hi>Laſt Appeal,</hi> wherein we are bound to <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce.</hi> Now this <hi>Power</hi> muſt be truſted in <hi>ſome</hi> hand, and <hi>That</hi> muſt of neceſſity be, where the <hi>Sovereign Power</hi> remaineth; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there muſt be ſuppoſed a <hi>Superiour Power</hi> to that <hi>Sovereign Power,</hi> and ſo <hi>in Infinitum,</hi> untill we come to ſome ſuch <hi>Power</hi> as hath nothing <hi>above</hi> it; and then <hi>That</hi> muſt be entruſted, and be ſubmitted to, without being accountable to <hi>Any</hi> but to <hi>God;</hi> becauſe on Earth there can be to it no <hi>Superiour Juriſdiction.</hi> And this Power is in the King of <hi>England</hi> in all things, ſuch onely excepted, wherein <hi>Himſelf</hi> or his <hi>Anceſtours</hi> have, by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Stipulations,</hi> limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their <hi>Abſolute Power;</hi> as was ſaid before. And <hi>This</hi> we are by the Law of <hi>God,</hi> and of the <hi>Land,</hi> bound to <hi>Obey,</hi> and not to make any <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> but what the <hi>Law</hi> alloweth us: We muſt, in the Reſt, have recourſe unto <hi>God,</hi> if our Princes be <hi>Wicked;</hi> neither may we <hi>Mutiny,</hi> or <hi>Repine</hi> at God, when we have <hi>Ill</hi> Kings, more than when he ſendeth Diſeaſes, Plagues, Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars, Blightings or Blaſts. For <hi>wicked</hi> Kings are but <hi>Blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> that God is pleas'd to Puniſh: neither muſt we think <hi>Our</hi> Condition <hi>worſe</hi> than that of <hi>Wicked</hi> Kings; (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their <hi>Temporall Impunity</hi>) for certainly it is much <hi>Better,</hi> both in regard of Puniſhment in the <hi>World to Come,</hi> and commonly in <hi>This.</hi> For the <hi>Next</hi> World as Their <hi>Sin</hi> is greater; ſo it is declar'd that their <hi>Puniſhment</hi> ſhall be greater alſo, <hi>Hear, Oye</hi> Kings, <hi>and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50738:5"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand, &amp;c. Becauſe, being</hi> Miniſters <hi>of</hi> Gods Kingdom, <hi>you have not judg'd aright, nor kept the Law, nor walked after the Counſel of God; horribly and ſpeedily ſhall he come upon you, for a ſharp Judgment ſhall be to them that are in</hi> High Places, <hi>for</hi> Mercy <hi>will ſoon pardon the</hi> Meaneſt, but Mighty men <hi>ſhall be</hi> mightily <hi>Tormented. Wiſd.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Whereas <hi>Subjects,</hi> who ſuffer with <hi>Patience,</hi> becauſe they are ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God, make him their <hi>Debtor</hi> by their <hi>Sufferings;</hi> and he always payeth faithfully, who ſaith, that <hi>if we</hi> ſuffer <hi>with</hi> Chriſt, <hi>we ſhall alſo</hi> Reign <hi>with him.</hi> And for this World, their <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> is ſtill accompanied with theſe Fears, Deſtractions, and Horrors of Conſcience, which have ever been inſeparable from <hi>Tyrannies;</hi> by which their Lives are render'd more uncomfortable, than the Unhappieſt of their <hi>Subjects.</hi> And for the moſt part, their <hi>Ends</hi> are as miſerable as their Lives; for what they <hi>Fear,</hi> and by their Tyranny ſeek to <hi>prevent,</hi> doth commonly fall upon them: Their People do <hi>Revolt</hi> and <hi>Rebel;</hi> and although they be never ſo well <hi>Chatechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> in the points of <hi>Obedience;</hi> yet their <hi>Natural Inclination</hi> to recover their <hi>Liberty,</hi> much more to caſt off <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Burthens,</hi> and Oppreſſions, is ſuch, that ſleight and weak <hi>Arguments</hi> will eaſily perſwade them to <hi>that,</hi> whereunto they are ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined, and the leaſt pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> or Colour of <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Lawfulneſs,</hi> countenancing or tolerating the <hi>Freeing</hi> themſelves from <hi>Subjection,</hi> in any Caſe, will be more prevalent with them, than the moſt paſſitive <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>God's Word,</hi> enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obedience. If in any caſe <hi>taking up Arms</hi> be admitted, <hi>theirs</hi> ſhall ever be <hi>that</hi> Caſe. And if the Wickedneſs of their Prince ſhall be allow'd as a ground of their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> their Prince ſhall ever be the moſt <hi>Wicked:</hi> Of all this, <hi>all</hi> Ages have produced many Examples, and eſpecially theſe <hi>Later</hi> Times, through all the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> And wicked Princes will find, that <hi>Precepts</hi> in this eaſe will not ſerve the <hi>Turn;</hi> for tho' <hi>Hoſtile Reſiſtance againſt the King</hi> be expreſly prohibited by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> both in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament;</hi> tho it be againſt the Doctrine and Practice of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> and the preſent <hi>Tenets,</hi> and <hi>Confeſſions of Faith,</hi> of all the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> in the World, though it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50738:6"/>to the Solemn <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Fidelity,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> ſworn to the King; rhe <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land (which make it <hi>Treaſon</hi>) and <hi>Moral Honeſty</hi> and Juſtice; yet will it be in this point of <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſays of <hi>Divinations</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi>) which was a <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> that had <hi>been, and ever</hi> would <hi>be</hi> forbidden, yet <hi>ever would be</hi> Retained: <hi>Semper Vetabitur, &amp; ſemper reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebitur.</hi> And ſo to Princes that will highly <hi>Oppreſs,</hi> and make their <hi>Will,</hi> and not the <hi>Laws,</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of their <hi>Government,</hi> although (I ſay) to <hi>reſiſt</hi> be a <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and that it be againſt the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to do it; yet where the <hi>Wrongs</hi> are Great, and a Fair <hi>Opportunity</hi> offer'd of <hi>Prevailing,</hi> it will be ever done: For that amongſt men, there are a <hi>Thouſand</hi> for <hi>One,</hi> that prefer their own <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Inclination,</hi> before <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> or <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And certainly, a Prudent and Foreſeeing Prince, that will impartially examine things, cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it ſhould be ſo. For why ſhould he ſuppoſe, that <hi>Other</hi> men will be more <hi>Honeſt,</hi> or more <hi>Religious</hi> than <hi>Himſelf?</hi> And when he breaks through all the Bonds and Ties of <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Divine Precepts</hi> and <hi>Moral Juſtice,</hi> only to ſtretch and extend his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs;</hi> why ſhould we not expect, that <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> ſhould make as bold to tranſgreſs the <hi>ſame</hi> Duties, in hope of Recovering <hi>Liberty;</hi> with even the <hi>Falſe ſhew,</hi> whereof People are apter to be further tranſported, than by any Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Deſire</hi> whatſoever? Neither will the Fear of <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Danger</hi> reſtrain them; becauſe they will not Attempt, untill <hi>Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity</hi> make them hopeful of <hi>Prevailing;</hi> and then they conſult by <hi>Power</hi> to provide for their own <hi>Impunities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> beſides this <hi>Proneneſs</hi> in <hi>People</hi> to be eaſily led and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into <hi>Rebellion,</hi> under the falſe and ſpecious Shew of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering <hi>Liberty;</hi> the great Monarchs and Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> have been (in great part) the Fomenters and Upholders of it, and their <hi>Doctors</hi> have not ſo much by their <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> beaten it down, as the <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves have, by their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> given Encouragement unto it; for although I ſhall ever ſpeak with Reverence of Princes and their Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, yet I ſhall hope that the humble Repreſentation of <hi>this,</hi> Truth will receive a fair Interpretation. For it is undeniably true, that in this <hi>latter</hi> Age, all the great Monarchies and States
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50738:6"/>of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> have been render'd unhappy by <hi>Inteſtine Warrs,</hi> which have been encourag'd (if not contriv'd and deſign'd) by <hi>one</hi> Chriſtian Prince againſt <hi>Another,</hi> every one countenancing and indulging <hi>Rebellion,</hi> untill it become his <hi>Own</hi> Caſe, and then he is offended. Of this I ſhall give no particular Inſtances, the Notariety of it is too great, and I fear every <hi>State</hi> may too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily apply it to what themſelves have done: And it may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, that the ſad Condition of many <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> at this preſent day, may exhibit ſomething of Gods <hi>Judgments,</hi> upon <hi>that</hi> Account, who hath ſaid; <hi>With what Meaſure ye mete, it ſhall be meaſur'd to you again.</hi> Mat. 7.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND wicked</hi> Kings, as they are ſure they ſhall not 'ſcape the ſevere <hi>Judgment</hi> of God in the <hi>next</hi> World (if they do believe the <hi>Scripture</hi>) ſo (if they will believe <hi>ancient Hiſtories</hi> of what has paſt in <hi>former</hi> Times, or their own <hi>Experience</hi> of what they ſee daily with their Eyes; or that they do believe that God will <hi>repay</hi> unto them that which they have either countenanc'd or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd againſt <hi>others</hi>) they muſt expect to have troubleſome and uncomfortable <hi>Lives,</hi> accompany'd with Hatred, Hazzard, and Infamy. And if <hi>theſe</hi> Conſiderations will not reſtrain them, yet <hi>We</hi> muſt not be <hi>Wicked,</hi> becauſe <hi>They</hi> are ſo: Neither will God admit of <hi>Recrimation</hi> for our <hi>Excuſe. Our</hi> Duty of <hi>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> is <hi>Poſitive,</hi> upon pain of <hi>Damnatition;</hi> from which no good <hi>Succeſs</hi> or <hi>Prevailing,</hi> can keep us, although it may ſave us from the <hi>Gallows.</hi> Beſide this great Hazard of our <hi>Souls, Moral Prudence</hi> teacheth us, that a <hi>Civil War</hi> which (I hope yet we have no great reaſon to fear) is commonly <hi>a Cure much worſe than the Diſeaſe:</hi> For no <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> nay no <hi>Tyranny,</hi> brings with it half thoſe Miſeries and Calamities, which of Neceſſity, do ever accompany an <hi>Inteſtine War. Wicked</hi> Kings may be cruel, covetous and licentious; yet <hi>their</hi> Oppreſſions and <hi>their</hi> Luſts are reſtrained to <hi>ſome Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> and to <hi>ſome Perſons:</hi> But in a <hi>War,</hi> Rapes, Murthers, Robberies, Sacriledges, and all manner of Impieties break in, and all ſorts of People are made miſerable, which the poor Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> has found true by ſad Experience; where, in the Space of <hi>five</hi> years on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (from 1641 to 1646) <hi>more</hi> was taken from the <hi>Subject,</hi> than would have been exacted by Subſidies, Projects, or any unjuſt Taxes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50738:7"/>whatſoever, by the <hi>worſt</hi> of Kings, in the Space of a <hi>Hundred</hi> and ſo were all other <hi>Wickedneſſes</hi> increas'd proportionably.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I SHALL</hi> conclude this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> with my humble and hearty Prayers to God Almighty to <hi>avert</hi> his heavy <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> (which the Multitude of our Sins may give us juſt Cauſe to dread) from this Nation; at preſent the moſt proſperous and flouriſhing of any in <hi>Europe;</hi> and that the <hi>publick Calamities</hi> that befell the Kingdom in the late unhappy <hi>War,</hi> and the lamentable <hi>Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> and <hi>Confuſions</hi> that were wrought by our Diſſentions, both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> may be a Leſſon to the People to value and eſteem <hi>Peace,</hi> and not ſo <hi>wantonly</hi> to engaage themſelves afreſh in <hi>New Miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
